[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software if slow QA processes bottleneck
you or your software engineering team
and you're releasing slower because of
it you need to check out QA wolf.com QA
wolf gets engineering teams to 80%
automated end-to-end test coverage and
helps them ship five times faster by
reducing QA Cycles from hours to minutes
with over 105 star reviews on G2 and
customer testimonials from salesloft
drada AutoTrader and many more you're in
good hands go to QA wolf.com to see if
they can help you squash the QA
bottleneck welcome to software
engineering radio I'm your host Bri
shanut I'm here today with Sham PanAm to
talk about SAS control planes sham is
the C diagnos previously sh has grown
and supported multiple High performing
and deeply technical engineering teams
at Google Cloud LinkedIn and several
startups both in the US and in Australia
Shri welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything I missed in your
intro that you'd like to add hey thanks
for uh having me here no your spot on
looking forward to chatting and sharing
and learning let's start with a brief
definition of SAS and it's growing
Market importance yeah so if you think
about your favorite applications
especially you know in the last 20 years
you had the rise of this whole Web 2.0
movement actually let's let's go back
even before that right you had your
traditional Enterprise applications
companies would create something they
would deliver it to users users would
use it usually with long long you know
development and deployment Cycles right
it came with its own costs and nuances
and after the Circa 2005 onwards there
was a rise of the whole whip 2.0
movement right where applications would
be developed in a more agile way there
would be more consumer focused and
obviously web being the main delivery
mechanism meant that companies could
iterate faster collect feedback faster
and Delight the users in a much more
itera faster fashion now I don't work
for slack I'm in no way affiliated with
slack but I find SL is a very good
example of of of this right your typical
chatting applications WhatsApp Facebook
Messenger they are your typical consumer
applications right you have one instance
as far as the user can see there's one
giant Global instance you would you
would send messages you would read
messages you would do other things in
those applications now Enterprises felt
there was a need for the same
applications within a more closed or or
bounded domain right how about just
messaging within Enterprises how about
just messaging maybe within a collection
of Enterprise or collection of teams so
if you look at slack slack is a classic
Enterprise you know SAS offering or or
or you know a B2B offering which is
really popular right and it forms a good
example of uh how you how you
differentiate SAS and non-sas offerings
now in a SAS offering it is really a
business model if you think about what
it means to be SAS I think there are
many definitions but the key principle
is it's a business model and and it's a
dely model that that really is driven by
what the business needs technology is
common or is used in in most
applications but how is important one
key thing is agility right when you want
to I mean a lot of successful companies
that offer SAS products they believe in
the idea that they have to adapt to what
the market needs what the customers need
and what the competition is doing so a
lot of SAS companies are looking at
trying out new pricing models newer
market segments looking at new customer
needs now there's also the need for
onboarding being frictionless now yes
onboarding onto the older or traditional
consumer applications was frictionless
you had your oo you had your sign up
sign you know login that's tied to
customer but here really your customer
is the Enterprise all right while you
may not have previe and visibility to
the end Enterprise's individual
customers you want to make sure that
enterprises themselves can onboard onto
your application with the most
frictionless way possible so this has to
be important you can't just say hey look
we will set up a few boxes with slack
running in a bunch of nodes in your data
center manually each time right can you
imagine how long that would take can you
imagine how long it would take to roll
out fix
uh deploy new new features so all this
has to be fictionist right and you know
you also have especially last 10 or so
years Regulatory and compliance has been
a huge huge huge influence in how
Enterprises want to adopt your
offering in fact there are so many
regulatory envir requirements like
soling clouds and you know data
residency that demand that their
application data compute all reside in a
single geography for example again I
pick slack as an example slack is owned
by Salesforce which is an American
company yes it is global but it's but
headquartered in in in America right a
government organization in Germany might
have strict demands that all instances
of Slack are running physically in three
or four locations in Germany right so
you need to ensure that happens and
again a lot of the Innovation doesn't
just come from the user interface those
are premium things there are customer
features that do get rolled out but
these kind of compliance Enterprise
business needs being taken care of is a
primary motivation for the Innovation
right and also the usage scale varies I
think WhatsApp a customer competitive
offering to slack again not in the same
thing I think does has about a billion
daily active users each sending a,
10,000 messages I maybe thousand
messages a day you know and they have to
be globally available like I would have
a WhatsApp instance I would log WhatsApp
for example chatting with chatting with
my family all the way in India or
Australia and they all have to be
available at the same time with
something that's more Enterprise like
slack or slacks Enterprise offering
those particular Global demands could be
uh softened right I might require that
my employees are all based in a single
geography so as long as they can they
can communicate I'm good so these are
some of the things that that
differentiate SAS versus your
traditional consumer offerings and how
you build the teams around this those
are influence how how you build your
stack around this that is influenced how
you look at metrics how you look at your
product Road mapping how you look at I
would even say culture like your team
culture all that's influenced so that's
why you know SAS offerings themselves
SAS the business model is growing quite
fast and and will be doing so for the
next foreseeable future I think and
these stats keep changing all the time
an interesting stat I found was that in
us alone the SAS Market is around half a
trillion annually right and and and
globally there are uh between 25 and 50k
SAS companies that are offering various
C services to various Enterprises
interesting let's move into the topic of
the session which is SAS control planes
can you give a definition of what a
control plane is and why it's important
right we started with slack as a
motivating example here right and and
you can think of this for almost any
application that an Enterprise need
needs so what is a control plane you
know if you look back to if you look
back to networking I mean the the the
terminology uh arose from the networking
era right you had your data centers data
centers would have switches switches
would connect
to and number of routers and routers
would offer bunch of networks right the
idea was you wanted some kind of
connectivity from one part of the world
that's the physical connectivity uh
going through some kind of logical
networking to another part of the world
right now at the start these were all
pretty much physically placed physically
created my career started off as a nwork
designer in a in in Australia's largest
Telcom called um telra and my job was
to design how to structure customer r
within a data center for their needs and
a lot of that involved and planning was
a huge part of that right you would kind
of ask them what the applications were
uh you know what was the typical usage
pattern of the application what kind of
Ingress egress you know in terms of
bandwidth needs they would need and you
would decide okay look we they'll need X
number of switches y number of routers
this is kind of given these kind of
isolation between their own topologies
they might need so and so number of
networks now obviously as and this was I
think early 2000s right as the Web 2.0
movement took on and scale was you know
scale was growing ODS of magnitude and I
exaggerate on a weekly basis right doing
this physically or manually was just not
possible take for example Google and
this is this is just me doing back of
the envelope numbers
right if you had to handle the traffic
that Google itself serves what happens
inside Google is actually larger than
what happens in all of the internet
outside uh I mean if you think of that
you know put the way Google's internal
traffic among the services amongst the
thousands and hundreds of thousand
Services
is greater than the amount of traffic
that the rest of the internet sees
outside right and that and that's a
staggering staggering fact so you can't
provision these networks manually you
have to have some way where these
networks can be can be provisioned
declaratively so this whole idea of a
highly connected cross switching fabric
came up right and again as a summary
what this gave you was the illusion of
every Network being connected sorry
every node in any network in the world
being connected to any other node almost
directly it wasn't directly obviously
right it would it would be through a
bunch of hops but you would change this
change this network topology using
software and that's where this whole
software defined networking came up
right and the thing that change these
routing rules not necessarily on the fly
on a on a second byc basis but on a
reasonable time frame that stack that
part of the stack was a control plane
right so yeah so how does all this you
know networking stuff appli to apply to
SAS I mean we're talking about something
that's eight layers above the networking
stack right so what what does what does
the networking stack have to do with
control planes and SAS right I mean
networking stack is layer one two maybe
three the application is you know four
five layers above that
now the idea is the same if you look at
you know again our favorite example
slack I think slack has something like
15 million daily active users as of
2023 2024 again my numbers are ran it up
right um now slack also has
about I think half a million sorry half
a million Enterprises on it right you
know 500,000 Enterprises roughly even if
you say that look most traffic to slack
is going to come from top 1% of
Enterprises now let's say 500k uh 1% is
what 5,000 Enterprises are contributing
to this 5 50 million daily active users
right again these are just
my back of the envelope numbers that I'm
uh envisaging so we're looking at 5,000
Enterprises contributing to 50 million
daily active users right and even if you
say look you know typical active user
if you define an active user as someone
sending let's say thousand messages a
day right we're looking at 50 billion
messages being sent today and that comes
to about I think half a million messages
per second right and again using some
very very hand wavy math if you assume
that for every message you send it is
being read by 20 users um in all these
channels you already have for half a
million messages being created about 10
million reads of those messages that's
staggering per second by the way and
that's a staggering number to serve this
you're looking at anywhere between you
know around 10,000 compute nodes with
about 10 terabytes of memory give or
take right now more interesting here is
that you can say look it's only it's
only 10,000 nodes let's just bring up a
giant instance of slack and be done with
it right now imagine you know 10,000
nodes serving 500,000 Enterprises
globally that's your classic shared
model where every Enterprise is being
served out of the same stack where is
the stack running is a stack running
globally is a stack running in some data
center in North America is this is it
running you know some in some Rand
configuration now we talked about how
Enterprises have these requirements on
how they want their applications to be
isolated right and isolation is the big
big motivation for what you're talking
about right if if it was a single
application cluster that you deploy
create and deploy once we don't need a
control plane right what customers want
is to be able to say look I want a stack
imagine if you're uber right Uber says I
want to Stack my usage is predicted to
be this I want to make sure that my
availability is so and so which means
that if I'm sharing a cluster with
499,000 other users then it's pretty
much a All or Nothing availability mode
if that cluster goes down every customer
is affected right as we can see that
forms the motivation of why you want
isolation now the go the other extreme
if you say that look every customer gets
their own separate cluster so these
10,000 nodes are serving you know 5,000
customers so two nodes per customer
rough hand VI math then the challenge is
how do you deploy these how do you
deploy these clusters when they when
they are needed right again the going
back to the old networking model of a
new customer comes in they want a
dedicated Network go and design your
switches and routers was great on day
one but now it's just very very
cumbersome so this way the control plane
comes in right the control plane is a
piece of software or it's part of the
stack that ensures that anything that
slack is not directly responsible for
for handling a new customer it takes
care of it so what are what are some of
those things Uber comes in they want to
use slack how do you onboard them is
there a console for them to onboard
quickly without having to submit a
request and wait few weeks before the
slack team goes and Provisions those
machines and infrastructure manually
right how do you handle any Regional
requirements if Uber says look I really
want to have everything in this region
or these regions for for so for so and
so availability are we expecting them to
go and manage their own like custom
clusters on which we'll install this
could be kubernetes or anything but we
don't want that billing we talked about
50 billion messages a
day those like that's not a that's not a
that's not an even distribution of
messages if you're charging somebody for
number of messages you want to actually
measure what that's like right or you
might just charge for a footprint right
and so on now now slack might even say
look we'll actually help you manage your
users identity and accounts and accesses
right so there's some overlap in does
that as to whether that belongs to the
control plan or the data plane uh by the
way the data plane is the is the
application being provisioned or managed
or deployed right I think in some places
it's also called the application plane
it is effec the service that the end
user SE right now what about things like
do you want to have any other specific
tenant provisioning details that you
want to abstract away so this this is
the control plane it is like any other
service but it helps build the different
stacks and deploy the different stacks
and provision different stacks and
tenants for the end Enterprise customer
right that is the key I suppose
definition like one one key definition
to Rally around right it has more
nuances like how it manages data how do
you get to that ideal state where do you
start from and so on but you can think
of the control plane as the service or
the plane that manages the life cycle
and availability of the data plane so
just to summarize you started off with
giving a brief history and how data
centers whiches and routers the
complexity was managed using software
and that kind of led to the creation of
a control plane which is primarily there
to manage provisioning configuration
user management charging Regional
deployments and so on for the data
planes or the applications is that a
good summary yeah so the idea of control
planes came from the networking world
right how you manage those tenant
specific non-end user specific concerns
is what the control plane is about can
you tell me a story of how control plane
help manage
complexity I think I I started off on
some parts of that in the previous
question right so think about you know
what are the what you would need to
deploy slack for you know its customers
and and I can talk some of the internal
examples too the reason I use slack is
because it's a very relatable example
that that people just get right well
first of all let's look at some of the
some of the core concerns that a control
plane should really really take care of
right there are many but I like to think
of them as metrics how do you help shine
usage metrics from the underlying
service both to the administrators of
that service let's say slack as well as
to the developers of the service right
so the control play needs to be able to
identify that look this instance is
being used in these ways and here are
all the rich metrics data that can be
captured uh to to shine light on how
different tenants are using the system
now you as a service developer can use
that that metric data to improve various
parts of your your your actual dat data
plane offering the other one is how are
you establishing the creation of tenants
sorry the life cycle of tenants not just
creation right you want to have what I
call the crud operators on tenants that
create retrieve or get update and delete
tenants right when you onboard a new new
tenant like Uber or apple onto slack
what do you set up for them before they
can start using slack right that might
take into account all their compliance
rules in fact an organization might
actually have multiple tenants right for
example you know someone like apple
might say again this is just this is not
based on any particular examples but
just general observations around
different SAS deployments right so Apple
might say look for my AI team I will
need this entire slack instance for
these set of users who are primarily in
North America that's one tenant within
apple or they might say one tenant is
here a second tenant could be in Europe
only for the legal area right now us
slack might think of Apple as one one
customer or one account but you might
decide that they themselves like
allowing multiple tenants to be there
for that one customer account is a
Paramount for you so now your control
planer needs the notion of what is a
tenant what is an account what is an
installation what is a deployment now
now that you created these tenants they
might say look I have you know different
kinds of onboarding I would like to
onboard my own user let's say strea.com
or Bridges apple.com right using my
internal employee IDs now how can I tie
up the authentication of those users
let's say it's based on o o or TFA and
so on before they log into slack right
now slack as a service might give you
those features for enabling different
kinds of authentication but you still
have to provision different data stores
so that you store that that information
in compliance with whatever Apple needs
and that could mean Apple gets their own
dedicated database of user accounts
right whereas somebody who's you know a
smaller startup with 10 10 customers
might be okay with not having those
strict isolation requirements right so
when you onboard them you might say look
I'll have 10 instances or 10 different
tenants running on the same internal
like my own kubernetes cluster where I'm
deploying slack so this kind of managing
of onboarding and resources for those
onboard attendants is is key now an
admin user can admin user interface can
be two different things here right one
is as the overall slack the company
offering you might have an interface to
Monitor and observe the different tenant
instalations it could also be an admin
interface for the tenant administrator
so somebody at Apple or somebody at your
you know let's say diagnos might be the
administrator for their respective
accounts so things like log in and
looking at you know operational
behaviors and be able to manage that
environment right if they want to
upscale what does that mean an upscaling
could mean hey look I I expect that I'm
going to have instead of 10 users I'm
going to have a thousand users so I'm
saving that now slack you go and take
care of provisioning without me caring
about those details so now slack the
slack the control plane will say look
now that I know this user let's say this
user is going from a small a very small
instance of 10 users to a large instance
of thousand users maybe they got funding
they got acquired they and so on right
now I need to make sure that I'm I move
that instance from a a shared host to
its own for example kubernetes cluster
and slack has to the slack control plane
is responsible of doing all that without
the end user noticing that this is
happening so now it has to manage this
kind of updates the update part life
cycle and the other important thing that
we we talked about is R like R
authentication how do you make it so
that you know the end user does not how
to manage these accounts manually but
they can use your offered features as
part of the control plane to have that
seamless onboarding within onboarding
and and what I mean by that is there's
the first Enterprise on boarding like
apple Uber level and then the individual
customer um individual employee or user
on boarding last but not least I think
building is the key thing ultimately you
know you you are doing a I mean you're
selling I mean you're in business
because you want to turn a profit right
or you want to I mean you have
certain growth or financial goals that
you want to meet and and without loss of
generality let's say you want to make
money and ultimately a large part of
bilding is know you know is knowing how
you are charging your you know your
customers on some metri could be it
could be it could be based on
subscriptions it could be based on usage
and you want this building to be fair
and transparent you know if you go back
to that V
0.0.1 where we said hey you know what we
have 10,000 nodes running slack every
slack Enterprise customer is you know in
part of that shade cluster how do you
know which customer had how much usage
that he can build in Fairly for so
building being robust and available and
not being you know being consistent and
available is important right so these
are the core core features that control
plane should be responsible for as soon
as possible now you can do this in
different ways you can do this through a
solid approach a a shared approach a
completely completely isolated approach
both on the data level and service level
and they have different implications and
we can talk more about that you talked
about data planes just wanted to
understand have you come across any
instance where the control plane and
data plane were not separated out and
how did that evolve over time did it
need to be separated out as has the
application
matured no this is a great great
question right most SAS offerings start
off as a single combined control plane
data plane offering and what I mean by
that is let's go back to slack slack on
its day one would have and again this is
not definite right any offering like
this would have looked like a giant
database where every you might have a
few tables in this database like a user
table you know at chat table a messages
table and each of these tables would
have a dedicated column called tenant ID
right where you might say you know for
this tenant or this Enterprise user get
me all chats where the tenant ID is this
right now what happens here is that you
have single table and and it's up to the
service itself to write the rules or WR
to layer out their business logic to
Route across different tenants and when
you're a new startup right this makes
sense because you want to focus more on
your business logic you really don't
want to invest in a separate control
plane team to handle these different
customers and part of that is also the
business motivation right because you
would start off with smaller customers
who are okay to be in this model if a
startup on day one acquired a large
customer then this would be the
focus then you have your uh Next Step
where instead of putting everything in a
single single database single you know
single schema right you might say look I
have my chats table I have my message
table I have my users table let me
create a different database or single a
different schema for each tenant so you
might say instead of having a messages
table I'll have Uber messages or
messages Uber as my table right or I
might even have a database called Uber
database which will have three different
these three different tables in it right
so at the code level you might say look
uh as soon as I get a request I will
look at which tenant that user belongs
to let's say use something like oo to
identify you know what that domain is
and so on right and you might say every
action from now on will go to this
database so my code is lightened at the
moment because I don't have to choose
between database on every operation I
make it has to happen at the at the
starting point again this is great
because you have you have slightly more
I mean you still sharing resources you
don't have to worry about you know
provisioning concerns the only
provisioning concern here is can I
create those three different tables in
that customer specific database in my in
my DB cluster right uh and this will go
on for a while this is fine the downside
is that again it is shared so if that
database cluster goes down all the
customers go down now as you evolve as
you have customers with
higher isolation requirements you'll
start offering you'll start looking
looking at okay how can I ensure that
each customer gets their own tenant
which means that within that tenant or
within that within that service stack or
service stack deployment right the code
looks at that entire stack as a single
tenant it is not aware of multiple
tenants because why would you right when
you have a single stack and is isolated
and it's dedicated to One customer it's
that's all it needs to focus on now
here's where you know you would start
thinking about how do I ensure that a
control plan concern is needed because
as custom number of customers grow you
don't want to manage these Stacks
manually you don't want to operate them
manually you don't want to manage them
manually one by one you want to do it in
automated fashion so this kind of is a
is a typical Evolution from everything
in a single name space or single share
environment for all customers to you
know something in between where you have
a hybrid approach of some customers
could be routed based on schema and some
customers could could get their own
dedicated clusters while it's manageable
all the way to a fully solid approach
where every customer is either play you
know either been packed into a shade
cluster based on their tier or gets
their own dedicated cluster based on
their tier and their requirements
obviously their revenue potential too so
yeah this is kind of a typical Evolution
from day one SAS day one SAS with
buil-in control plane all the way to a
dedicated control plane team or
organization that supports the different
products that a company might offer
thanks we'll now move to the next
section which is more around designing
the SAS control plane can we start off
by walking through a how data movement
happens in a typical SAS setup and what
are the interjections where the control
plane helps that data movement let's see
uh we covered a few things before uh in
terms of isolation yeah so let's look at
first of all how we want to think about
storage and data for your both the
control plane Services as well as the
data plane needs in terms of storage and
data we spoke about you know different
partitioning models you know on day one
you have everything in a single database
single data store or single data cluster
right or or data name space and then the
software is responsible for deciding
which table or or which row to pick
based on the tenant ID and as we Evol to
the next level of partitioning the
software has a top level routing of
which database or which name space to
pick and then after that you can think
about a dedicated database connection
that is only for single database or
single schema being handled by the
underlying code so in a way it's not
really tenant aare fully but it uses the
different database instances and then
going the full extreme we talking about
every customer getting their own data
cluster or data name space or database
now they have like each of these each of
these storage partitioning schemes right
or or or routing schemes they have their
own approach on how they can manage data
migrations right if you look at the
fully fully independent isolated model
the the control plane can help migrate
data on a pertinent basis right because
it is either moving an entire database
or it's just moving an entire database
cluster from you know one location to
another in the middle case where we said
I will assign multiple like you know a
unique name space for every customer
replicating that or moving that out is a
relative easier proposition imagine
having to filter in a single database
for tenants by tenant ID when you have
to that means that you're incurring a
load on a single database right now
doing this in a in a um in a solid like
in a solid approach right means that
there you can do a continuous backup of
your data or or your database for that
tenant and simply restart or or load
from that back up in the event of a
Handover or failure or transition from
you know leader to follower so the thing
is whichever strategy you pick the
control plane has to have a certain set
of rules on what kind of automation it's
running to ensure that this replication
bringing bringing back up restarting uh
procedures taken care of right and data
uh replication is part of this uh
Disaster Recovery is part of this so
this also affects how you have your RPO
and RTO targets
and obviously all that's impacted by the
cost that the customer is willing to
incur right the other aspect of data
migration data movement is security
consideration right obviously when you
have all the data in a single tenant or
or single cluster in the day one
scenario you need extra extra security
processes right both both at the
business logic level at the access level
in all parts of your stack to ensure
that you don't have data being leaked
across tenants right it gets easier as
you go up the isolation strategy stack
right in the case of multiple databases
in the same or multiple name space in
the same database it's a bit easier in
the case of multiple clusters or
dedicated clusters or dedicated tenants
it's a lot easier right it's a lot more
it's a lot more uh easy to ensure that
kind of security guarantee the other
part of data management is also U
building and how you ensure you know the
kind of Roi I suppose right when you
have a single tenant sorry when you have
a single cluster where all tenants are
hosted you are saying that the worst
case scenario or the best case scenario
or best kind of instances will be given
to everybody whereas here you have much
more access to sorry you have much more
you have an opportunity to give much
more fine grain access on giving the
right kind of instances for the right
customers customers who are willing to
pay more can enjoy better instances or
better clusters customers who are okay
with lower levels of isolation and lower
slos they they can stay on the shade TI
until needed right so yeah so the
control plane gets more and more robust
and gets more and more complicated
because it has to manage this data
movement across tiers across security
boundaries across isolation boundaries
across Regional constraints and do and
has to do so in a more changing
environment this demand won't change on
a regular basis but when it does it has
to do it you know with minimal downtime
with you know minimal manual
intervention and with as much uh uh with
as quick of a turn around as
possible all right can you talk about
some interesting architectural decision
points and common patterns used in
designing a control plane so one thing I
can share we talked about the example of
a a very large company wanting multiple
tenant
for their own architecture right now if
you look at this the three models we
spoke about so far we said look on day
one a starts offering has everything
bundled in day five or somewhere in
between it starts split out the data or
the the data or some parts of the
services into their own namespaces and
then you have completely dedicated
offerings for each customer if you were
to go the the extra step right there are
you can think of this as a control plane
of control plane architectures right now
imagine a very large company wanting
their own isolated tenants on their own
premises now these premises could be
actual data centers or they could be
custom Cloud accounts right U either
customer accounts on AWS or
organizations on Azure and so on right
if you look at some of the large scale
data processing platforms right for
example data flow it would provision an
entire working stack or a large part of
the provision working stack on the
customer account that means bringing up
the computer instances the storage notes
the GPU instances and so on right on the
customer service account and running the
jobs on there right so there is the
control plane that clearly orchestrates
their instance and then within that you
have a control plane which is
responsible for orchestrating things
locally right so this architecture where
you have your initial control plane that
deploys under the control plane on the
customer premise is pretty interesting
because you you really talking about
another level of isolation and another
level of control the customer can
benefit from this obviously is pretty is
is adds to complexities right because in
the true SAS model you're provisioning
you're provisioning customers offering
in an environment that you're familiar
with right right the moment you have to
transcend that and go to a different
environment it obviously adds more scope
for failures for you know more
challenges in terms of availability more
challenges in terms of being able to
observe and monitor and debug what's
happening on the tenant side right this
idea of having control plane off control
planes is actually a pretty interesting
design choice now obviously you wouldn't
do that from day one it's it's reserved
for the ultra Ultra
sensitive customers you know who have
those strict isolation requirements even
beyond what you might provide on your
own can you tell me about any instance
or any stories where something has gone
wrong and how was it detected and then
resolved so at diagnos we are very a
large part of our footprint is around
provisioning our software or our
offering directly on the customer
premises right so we do follow a control
plane off control plane models but at a
much smaller scale right now the Big
Challenge here is depending on the
customer they might have security
regulations and security requirements
where they may not be able to share
observability data and metrics back to
us at diagnos we offer tools for running
automations for the customers you know
in a much more frictionless way right so
so when so when we offer a share or even
a managed offering of that diagnose it's
easy to it's easy to debug them because
we know what what's going wrong when
customers observe any failures we can we
can trace through our typical observ
stack right now when things are going
wrong on their premises it gets
challenging right so what we have done
is we actually enabled instrumentation I
mean like we enabled observability
stacks on those offerings as well right
but because of uh challenges in having
them export that to us we made it so
that we can only get the observability
data from them when and how they choose
to send it right so the downside of this
is that when failures happen they will
be the first to be alerted this requires
them to have their own observability
teams or at least a small ability team
to be on standby when failures happen
and we train them we train them so that
they can trage these incidents and
escalate to us or or reach out to us
after a certain tier now what we've done
is we've made it simple to we made it
simple for them to share these metrics
for us on a
more dialable basis right so they can
choose how much they want to share to us
so some customers are more particular
about logs because they they may hold
sensitive information some customers are
okay with sending everything so we found
that just by sending us trace and
metrics we were able to help them more
secure way faster customers are okay
sending everything even better obviously
when they share less or when when when
they share less even though they have
the choice to do so they have a higher
time to resolution but that's that's as
expected from this architecture right so
the key here is when they you know we'
instrumented we've added we've added
inst mentation both in the control plane
and in the data plane right or the
application plane so that this instrum
instrumentation can be filtered on both
sides both on the customer side as well
as on our side so they have some
guarantee that they aren't leaking too
many things to us or they aren't leaking
things to us that are that they wouldn't
want to and obviously as customers see
that you know customers that want are
okay with this they can dog this all the
way to the right and have a much faster
resolution and detection because we are
now privy to the patterns of usage and
errors on their side so the control
plane having this variability in how it
provisions and what it provisions on the
customer stack and being able to upgrade
that again with with the full control of
the customer is a very important choice
that helps us do you have or do you
remember any observation or any data
shared by the customer which surprised
you what were the findings well I can't
share it there's always surprises
there's
always there are always surprises that
turn out to be not surprising once you
get to the bottom of
it right yeah because we we've had many
customers that I mean would obviously
see a failure depending on how much
they're exporting to us you know we
would be we would have visibility into
what's causing it again to keep it at a
very general level we had I can show you
this one of our customers was using our
one of the control plane data stores for
their own data plane logging it wasn't
so much a bug as much as a design choice
I
guess and this obviously affected their
building right because when we build
them the building was based on usage and
not necessarily things like storage
metrics now obviously when storage was
ballooning because of this work around
our flaw we obviously found a way to
mitigate that at that point in time but
it also helped us learn how we can
address the issue of building up front
and what kind of metering has to be in
place to catch all the right metrics so
again so we can provide a fair price to
our customers right again this is a very
simple this a very specific example of
plane storage leading onto our control
plane uh which we're able to identify by
observing how they're using it are the
architectural approaches different for
control planes and multi-end solutions
the architectural approach is different
for control planes in multi- Solutions
in a way you you are creating control
plane to make multi M tendency easy
right now we talked about now we talked
about different kinds of multi tendency
from day one to day five to day 100
right even that at logical level the
single cluster or single physical
physical environment with all your
customers all your tenants in there if
you think about it is multi tenanted
right now the isolation is what has
changed right as the as the offering
grows as the shape of the offering grows
as the scale grows your control plane is
evolving on where it is deploying this
logical entity right now when it's
deploying yet another table or yet
another uh yet another tenant ID in a
single database that your single stack
can use versus yet another physical
cluster to be used by a tenant all the
way to a dedicated control plane on the
customer's premise your control plane is
going to change right in fact your
control plane storage itself
is going to evolve you must start
putting more and more things in the
control plane storage right so that
there are different availability
guarantees uh in fact you want your
control plane to be highly consistent
right if you think about the crud
operations on a control plane your crud
operations on a control plane will map
to the crud operations on the life cycle
of your tenant going back to slack there
are 50 billion slack messages today
right but there're only what 500 ,000
slack Enterprise accounts right even if
even if slack was growing let's say 100%
uh 100% year on year right you might add
500,000 more slack accounts or slack
Enterprises uh Enterprise accounts next
year but that is still a a tiny tiny
tiny drop compared to how many messages
are being sent by slack so it's okay for
your slack control plane to be to have a
higher latency but it needs to have
higher availability right so that
obviously affects the choice in how you
design and what kind of storage You' use
and you know when you write to the
storage what kind of transactionality
you might want to impose at the expense
of latencies right so yeah so so yes
your your design CH choices do change
your control plan Al does change but you
have to remember the control plane
itself is much much lower in footprint
than your data plane and it has to be
right you want to ensure that you're
powering a scale that is OD as more than
what the control plane itself would see
in fact you want your control plane to
be built built in such a way that even
if your control plane goes down your
data plane continues to operate yes you
might not be able to create a new tenant
right but but your existing tenants are
still operating you might not be able to
delete a tenant okay that's fine you
might not be able to change the shape of
a tenant temporarily while the control
plan is being brought up again right but
you know your data plane has to be
operating operating at a much much
higher level of availability because
that's what the end user is going to see
right so yeah so ultimately your control
plane has to enable multi tendency right
that Journey from day one where
everything is in one place to day you
know X where you have control planes
control planes or some hierarchy of that
that's an interesting
Journey what are the disaster recovery
considerations that we need to consider
when designing the control plane we
touched briefly on this on the data
movement migration aspects of of this
Frame if you think about a control plane
as any other service after all it is a
service right it's a service that's
managing the life cycle of other
services a control plane is going to
have its own Disaster Recovery
mechanisms because it's going to have
its own storage and data that it has to
it has to uh ensure right for example a
control plane storage might keep track
of what is the
application positioning or placement in
different regions for a particular
tenant Apple for example has five
tenants have n number of clusters in 25
different regions may be Spread spread
out across the three major clouds so
recording all this is a key
responsibility amongst many others of
the control plane and we spoke about how
it needs to have high consistency and
high availability at the expense of
latency it can trade off latency for
availability and uh consistency so just
like any other service you might choose
how you do Disaster Recovery by picking
a second picking one or more secondary
regions where you're doing either real
time or some RPO based replication you
might be okay if if for example a
company says a tenant says I'm okay with
not being able to shape reshape my in my
slack instances for three hours then
that kind of forms your soft RTO right
or a recovery time objective so it has
very similar I mean the ideas you would
pick for Disaster Recovery would be
similar to any other service now if the
application if the if the data plane has
its own Disaster Recovery requirements
right for example if the data plane or
if Apple for example says I want mine
instances or all my messages to be
backed or to be replicated in three
different regions in three different
continents now you can leave it all to
the service to handle or you could
provide certain Plug-In or pluggable
some areas of pluggability in your data
plane that can communicate with the
control plane to make this happen so how
the different regions for Dr on the data
plane are set up could also be part of
your control plane concern right so tldr
a control plane is just a service it'll
have its own dis Disaster Recovery
mechanism but it can also help the the
data plane with some of those concerns
on placement on RTO IPO on setting up
the different environments for the
failovers and so on right so Dr has a
lot of similarities has a lot of
differences on what it means for control
plane but if you think of it as a yet
another service it makes the design
choices more
familiar thinking along a similar lines
what about security considerations for
for the control plane security
considerations for the control plane
again we can talk about the similarities
if you were to think of it as you know
yet other service right but one thing to
understand is many people when they
think about
isolation they fall back to
authentication and authorization right
this is not a wrong thing when you're in
day one and everything you is in a
single physical environment because we
talked about how the service layer is
now doing the routing at the table level
right by looking at a we CLA on the
tenant right but again there is very
little isolation here Beyond some piece
of code knowing which entries to fetch
in a table right but as you go up that
scale of everything shared to everything
being in a hierarchy you know control
ples of control planes right we talking
about how the control plane
enables plugging in
of custom and diverse access management
controls do you want access management
to be tied purely based on oath right
where you would log in through your
Google account and if you have a stre at
Apple and Bridges at google.com is that
enough versus I don't even want s at
Apple to be anywhere near the physical V
you know anywhere near a certain blast
radius vicinity of bridges google.com
right so again you can leave all this at
the data plane and you can say hey data
plane you manage which authentication
domains to connect to right but the fact
that the data plan is even letting you
choose between between authentication
domains could in itself be a major
security reflect at least uh security
concern as far as the many compliance
requirements could ensure so you might
want to say that this stack or this
setup or this deployment has to be
completely completely unaware of any
other the deployment anywhere else right
which means this deployment is access
management hooks into Azure versus that
deployment a management hooks
into aws's IM facilities has to has to
be managed and the control plane is what
can do that right we can extend this
example to control planes and control
planes where you might say that control
plane subset X only has access to help
you provision on Azure control plane
subset why only lets you provision your
deployments on gcp and so on right so
again you can expand the scope of the
control plane but it becomes a feature
of the control plan now like a feature
of any other service right to give you
the fine grain isolation of the various
access and authorization Primitives
depending on what the ation and customer
needs are tldr it's a feature but the
devil's in the details right what's the
role of kubernetes in the design of
control
planes so kubernetes lets you not as an
expert but kubernetes lets you create
clusters at scale right with ease it's a
very simplistic definition now your
clusters could be Regional your clusters
could be zonal your clusters could be in
different isolation boundaries that
you're willing to pay for right the the
main idea is that it takes away the
hassle of elasticity it takes away the
hassle of moving your workloads within a
cluster it takes away the hassle of of
of being able to do all the provisioning
that that that was much more harder and
finicky uh before right it also comes
with a lot of challenges right it it's
obviously a a very battle hardened piece
of infrastructure that that has you know
a whole bunch of skill sets that you
need uh it's obviously comp complicated
but at all that complexity you have I
mean you're able to enjoy the elasticity
that that you don't have to manage
yourself right before this you had to
mean even with VMS right you had to go
and manage it you had to observe it you
had to build up your Autos scaling
groups you had to T take care of a lot
of the you know provisioning and
deployment and R that facilities that
kubernetes gives you out of the box
right so if you think about how I would
use kubernetes to deploy either control
plane or a stack or or or a deployment
right if you go back to the day one
where everything was on a single service
your kubernetes cluster would be very
very would actually first of all be an
Overkill you're using kubernetes to
provision a set of resources a set of
very related resources and a very tight
boundary right whereas now with managed
Kos offerings like you know eks and you
know gke and eks right on Azure sorry on
uh AWS gcp and Azure respectively you
can create clusters on demand you can
provision your entire stack on them on
demand so the control plan's role now
would be to provision these clusters
with certain limits certain certain
resource requirements and constraints as
a customer sees fit these clusters could
also be running on the Enterprise
customers own premises right so kuet
makes all this easily easy because it's
a very unified way of of of
having resources and compute and you
know at scale with
elasticity right so it makes it makes
the the c u and D aspects much more
easier in your uh control plane that
create update and delete aspects
right there's obviously a lot more to
what goes on a deployment than just
resources in a cluster but it's a great
way to start off with you know the
resources that you might need without
having to incur provisioning delays and
and manual provisioning
complexity yep got it let's talk about
some of the future directions in the
space What emerging technology do you
see in this control plane
space so we spoke about control plane or
control plane architectur right the idea
really is how do you move the control
plane responsibility control plan
benefits or even its Administration
closer to the customer can you tell us
about any success stories that stand out
in your mind about using control
planes yeah so data flow is a really
great example you know data flow is
Google's data injection platform it's
actually built uh on top of an internal
platform called Flume and Flume traces
back its roots to the original map R use
idea right and data flow data flow and
flu are both unified you know batch and
streaming data processing platforms now
data flow itself is it's a highly
scalable highly available data
processing platform right it it
processes I believe something in the
order of tens of uh uh exhibites of data
across thousands of jobs a day right and
again doing very very high level numbers
its own footprint is in the order of of
you know tens of thousands of notes you
know across many many jobs that it runs
right its memory Footprints goes to is
not of pedabytes right and this is
powered by you know a very efficient
very scalable control plan that ensures
that customers jobs actually run on
customers accounts right in in a highly
available and scalable manner even
though it's a managed offering and not
necessarily A open source offering right
its control plane has been built on
years and years of research into you
know High skill engineering right and if
you look at uh other examples I mean
even a diagnose though we don't operate
at data flow scale our control plane is
currently at a more hybrid approach we
are scaling towards offering control
planes for our customers on their on
their premises which you know allow us
to dial how much metrics we can get from
the customers to help them at their own
behest right and we're obviously growing
and learning and applying better ideas
as we improve so yeah so again I guess
uh time will tell on how big and
scalable it you know it grows I think
that was quite insightful Shri as we
wrap up was there anything that we
missed that you would like to mention
yeah you know there's a lot of influence
and impact on you know building SAS
products on how one would structure
engineering teams now building a
consumer platform or or or consumer
offering while it's very very involved
and and complicated I think there are
certain similarities and differences
right in both you know Technologies Fast
Pace things are moving obviously with
you know with AI there's a lot of
there's a lot one can do in terms of
Building Services fast right some of the
differences could be more consumer
environment you have more
deeper placement of skills you would
find that you know engineering teams are
often specialized around certain areas
for mainly for product engineering teams
whereas in SAS offerings you might need
teams that are they have more expertise
in certain domains right you might want
to have teams that are very focus on
cloud computing or Cloud engineering
security compliance and these come
together pulling the functional
expertises in building SAS offs there
are challenges because doing
experimentation is a bit more unified
for for a product uh for for for a
consumer product right because you're
looking at how you would take feedback
from customer uh experience in a fairly
uh homogeneous way whereas how your
different customers your Enterprise
customers use your product there's a bit
more variation in SAS offerings right
again if you look at SAS offerings
there's more emphasis on Enterprise
features like management consoles
building features how you do isolation
uh compliance requirements those are a
bit more pronounced in SAS offerings
which may be hidden away for from
engineering teams at or or or they are
more localized in expertise in in you
know purely prodct engineering teams
right and also this is changing these
days the user experience requirements
also change a fair bit right and again
you know your your uh SAS offerings
depending on the kind of product may be
more engineering Le especially if the
SAS offering is a lot more engineering
focused as opposed to Dedicated product
management needs on a more consumer
product yeah and there's a lot more but
these These are the main ones that come
to mind thank you Shri for coming on the
show it's been a real pleasure this is
bries Aman for software engineering
radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening